Guide to the Henry Heald Speeches MC.50
New York University Archives
Henry Heald Speeches
1952-1956
New York University Archives
Heald, Henry T. (Henry Townley), 1904-1975
MC.50
0.75 Linear Feet in three half manuscript boxes
The Henry Heald Speeches contain numerous addresses, interviews, and commencement speeches made by Henry T. Heald between 1952 and 1956, while he was Chancellor of New York University.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open without restrictions.
Arrangment
This collection is arranged chronologically.
Biographical Note
Henry Townley Heald was born on November 8, 1904, in Lincoln, Nebraska. He obtained his bachelor's degree in 1923 from Washington State University and went on to get his master's degree in civil engineering from the University of Illinois. He went on to work at the Illinois Institute of Technology, eventually becoming President in 1938. Following his tenure there he became the Chancellor of New York University in 1950, where he helped strengthen the institution. He was an outspoken proponent for evaluating and restructuring higher education with an outlook toward accessibility for all. In 1956, Heald became President of the Ford Foundation. During his ten years as foundation president, the Ford Foundation gave $1.75 billion towards philanthropic purposes and established programs for the arts, the physical sciences, and engineering. Henry T. Heald died on November 23, 1975 in Winter Park, Florida.
Scope and Contents
The Henry Heald Speeches contain more than 100 speeches and addresses made by Henry T. Heald between 1952 and 1956, when he was Chancellor at New York University (NYU). Included are addresses on the importance of higher education, the future of NYU, engineering, and the connection between education and freedom.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Provenance is undocumented.
Engineering; Radio addresses, debates, etc.; Speeches.; Interviews.; New York University -- Chancellors; Ford Foundation
- Suggestions for the HTH Remarks at Catholic Dedication, 1952-02-06 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- HTH Remarks, 64th Annual Dinner, NYU Law Alumni Assoc., Inc., Waldorf Astoria Grand Ballroom, 1952-02-19 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- HTH Remarks, Medical Center Dinner, 1952-02-28 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- HTH Address at NYU Alumni Dinner, 1952-03-27 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- HTH, "Education's Challenge," Speech at Washington Award Dinner, Chicago, 1952-04-21 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- HTH Address, American Foundation for Pharmaceutical Education, New York City, 1952-04-24 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Address before Educational Alumni Association, 1952-04-25 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- HTH Remarks, National Conference of Christians and Jews Dinner, Brotherhood Awards to John Foster Dulles and Samuel Daniel Leidesdorf, 1952-05-12 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- HTH Remarks of Welcome, Hall of Fame Ceremony -- Susan B. Anthony and Thomas Paine, 1952-05-18 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Excerpts from HTH's Address to the Medallion Group, 1952-05-22 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- HTH Installation Address, 120th Commencement, 1952-06-11 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- HTH, Interview on WOR Radio. Recorded June 9, 1952 for Broadcast 6 p.m., June 11, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- HTH Remarks, SMPTE Meeting, NYU, School of Education Auditorium, 1952-06-25 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- HTH Remarks, Summer Session Assembly, School of Education, Education Auditorium, 1952-07-03 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- HTH, "Science Looks Ahead," Remarks at Evening Engineering Graduation, Gould Library Auditorium, University Heights, 1952-07-15 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- HTH, Talk at the first meeting of the Metropolitan Section, ASCE, for the 1952-1953 year. "The Engineer Becomes a University President" (Box 1, Folder 16)
- HTH, "New York University Looks Ahead," Radio Broadcast No. 1, WYNC., 1952 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- HTH, "Private Colleges and Universities Need Money," Article in Challenge Magazine, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- HTH, "A Chance to Serve," Speech before New York Chamber of Commerce of the State of New York, 1952-11-06 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- HTH Remarks, Cornerstone Ceremony -- Medical Center, 1952-11-07 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- HTH Remarks, RESA Initiation (Scientific Research Society of America), George Washington Hotel (Washington Room), New York, 1952-11-13 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- HTH, "The Volunteer in Education," Speech at Lane Bryant Award Luncheon, 1952-11-17 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- HTH Remarks at Dedication of the Wallace Clark Center for International Management. Lassman Hall, Commerce Building, 1952-12-04 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- HTH Radio Address, "NYU Serves the Community," Broadcast No. 2 -- WYNC, 1953-01-09 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- HTH Talk, Clarkson College Alumni, Philadelphia, PA., 1953-01-10 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- HTH Address, "Education and Public Policy," Annual Meeting of the American Institute of Electrical Engineers, Hotel Statler, New York City (Press release sent out January 16, 1953), 1953-01-19 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- HTH Speech, "The Faculty Role in University Administration," School of Education Faculty -- NYU, 1953-01-19 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- HTH Address, "Our Community Responsibility," before Protestant Council of Churches, New York City., 1953-01-26 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- HTH Address, "The Challenge of the 1960's: Today's Children Reach College Age," Barnard Forum, Waldorf Astoria Hotel, 1953-02-14 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- HTH Address, "Education and Freedom," Rollins College, 1953-02-22 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- HTH Talk, University Club Luncheon, 1953-03-21 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- HTH Address, "The University in an Urban Community," East Side Forum, New York City., 1953-04-14 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- HTH Remarks, Dental Alumni Dinner, Waldorf Astoria Hotel, 1953-04-24 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- HTH Remarks, "Report on the University," Medical Alumni Dinner, Waldorf Astoria Hotel, 1953-06-04 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- HTH Remarks, COUNCIL Dinner, Hotel Pierre, 1953-06-09 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- HTH, "Commencement Welcome," New York University, University Heights., 1953-06-10 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- HTH, Commencement Address at Northwestern University, 1953-06-15 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- HTH Address, "Slum Prevention: A Public Necessity," before the Metropolitan Housing and Planning Council of Chicago, 1953-06-16 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- HTH Remarks, "You and the University," School of Education Convocation (for New Students and Parents), Education Auditorium., 1953-09-29 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- HTH Remarks, United Nations Dinner, Delegates Dining Room, United Nations, 1953-10-06 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- HTH Talk, "A Task for Volunteers," Annual YWCA Lunchon, Plaza Hotel., 1953-10-14 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- HTH Remarks, Annual Engineers Dinner -- ECPD, 1953-10-16 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- HTH Remarks, Military Science Building Cornerstone Ceremony, University Heights Campus., 1953-11-04 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- HTH Talk, "The Citizen's Part," New York Tuberculosis and Health Association Annual Conference, New York, 1953-11-05 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- HTH Address, "Purposes of the Conference -- As Seen By the Educator," Industry - College Conference, White Sulphur Springs, W. VA., 1953-11-12 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- HTH Talk, "Unity in Diversity," Annual Meeting of the Middle States Association, Atlantic City, New Jersey, 1953-11-27 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- HTH Talk, "The Volunteer Layman", YMCA Report Luncheon, Hotel Commodore, New York., 1954-01-08 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- HTH Statement, on the Proposed Washington Square Southeast Redevelopment Project, Board of Estimate Hearing, 1954-01-26 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- HTH Remarks, Freshman Orientation, 1954-02-03 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- HTH Remarks (for recording), Nothern California Alumni Club, 1954-04-06 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- HTH Remarks, WSC Faculty Meeting, (On Liberal Arts, University, Etc.)., 1954-04-06 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- HTH Address, " The Responsibility of the Professions to the Future Society," Albany, New York, 170th Anniversary Convocation of the Board of Regents of the University of the State of New York, 1954-04-09 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- HTH Address, "Pattern of Progress," American Society of Tool Engineers, Philadelphia. (Speech not delivered due to death of HTH's father), 1954-04-29 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- HTH Address, "The Urban Institution in Higher Education," inauguration of Dr. Francis H. Horn as President of Pratt Institute, Brooklyn, New York., 1954-05-15 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- HTH Remarks, WATV, on higher education, 1954-06-07 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- HTH Remarks, NYU Commencement, 1954-06-09 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- HTH Commencement Address, "Means and Ends," at Newark, College of Engineering, 1954-06-10 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- HTH Remarks, Dedication of Riverdale Temple, New York City, 1954-09-19 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- HTH Address, "The Next 25 Years in the New York Metropolitan Region," before New York University Regional Plan Association, 1954-10-06 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- HTH Remarks, University Heights, Chapel Exercises, not used, 1954-10-07 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- HTH Remarks, Opening Centiennial Convocation of NYU's College of Engineering at the University Heights Campus, 1954-10-12 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- HTH Remarks, Annual dinner -- American Council on Education, 1954-10-14 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- HTH Address, "Education for Safe Living," National Safety Council, Chicago, 1954-10-18 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- HTH Address, Association of American Medical Colleges, French Lick, Indiana., 1954-10-19 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- HTH Remarks, Gould Center Dedication (Student Center), 1954-10-30 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- HTH Speech, "A Trustee's Responsiblity," Association of Governing Boards of State Universities and Allied Institutions., 1954-11-16 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- HTH Remarks, Institution of Mathematical Sciences, NYU, 1954-11-29 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- HTH Remarks, Jewish Culture Foundation Dinner for Moss and Hornstein, Waldorf, Starlight Room, New York City., 1954-12-09 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- HTH Welcoming Remarks, Modern Language Association, Hotel Statler, New York City., 1954-12-28 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- HTH Remarks, "An Appreciation of Franklin," Biltmore Hotel, New York., 1955-01-17 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- HTH Remarks, Midwinter Convocation -- College of Engineering, University Heights., 1955-01-29 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- HTH Address, "Every Age is an Age of Crisis," North Central Association, Chicago, Illinois, 1955-03-25 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- HTH Remarks, Foreign Language Conference, Hotel New Yorker, New York City., 1955-04-01 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- HTH Address, "The Second Mile," Greater New York Fund., 1955-04-25 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- HTH Remarks, National Association of Education Buyers -- New York, 1955-05-02 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- HTH Remarks, Overseas Information Conference at NYU, 1955-05-06 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- HTH Remarks, Alumni Federation Farewell dinner for DD Henry, Ambassador Hotel, New York, 1955-05-10 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- HTH Remarks, Commencement -- Nursing Graduates of St. Luke's Hospital, New York City, 1955-05-18 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- HTH, "Pathways to Progress," Commencement Address, University of Wichita, 1955-05-29 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- HTh Statement, at Dedication of Loew Dormitory, University Heights Center, 1955-10-08 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- HTH Remarks, Christ Church Annual Dinner, 1955-11-07 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- HTH Remarks as Chairman, First General Session -- Building for Brotherhood Dedication Program, Waldorf Astoria, West Ballroom, New York, 1955-11-09 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- HTH Remarks, "Why New York?," Wayfarer's Club, Chicago, 1955-11-22 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- HTH, Welcoming Remarks, Commerce Dean's Day, 1955-12-02 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- HTH Remarks, National Conference of Christians and Jews, Waldorf Dinner, 1955-12-07 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- HTH Remarks, Luncheon Meeting of the Municipal Forum of New York, 1956-02-09 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- HTH Remarks, New School for Social Research, New York City, cornerstone laying, 1956-02-11 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- HTH Remarks, Congregation of B'Nai Jeshurun, New York City, 1956-02-19 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- HTH Remarks, "Role of a Law Center in a University," Law Alumni Dinner, 1956-03-12 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- HTH Remarks, Arts and Engineering Alumni Meeting, University Heights, 1956-03-15 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- HTH Remarks, Beth Israel Hospital School of Nursing Graduation, New York City, 1956-03-20 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- HTH Remarks, "Youth: America's Most Vital Asset," Jewish Welfare Board Biennial Convention, New York City, 1956-04-05 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- HTH Introduction of French Ambassador, Waldorf Astoria Hotel, New York, 1956-04-06 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- HTH, "An Educator Looks at Industry," Industry-Education Conference, Hofstra College, 1956-04-17 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- HTH Remarks, Westchester Science Fair, 1956-04-20 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- HTH Remarks, for Tau Beta Pi, 1956-04-21 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- HTH Remarks, Times Square Club Honoring Roy E. Larsen, 1956-04-29 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- HTH Outline, Management Club Talk, NYU, 1956-05-04 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- HTH Remarks, Alumni Medallion Dinner, NYU Faculty Club, 1956-05-17 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- HTH Remarks, Hall of Fame Ceremonies -- Woodrow Wilson Bust, University Heights, 1956-05-20 (Box 3, Folder 30)
- HTH Remarks, "Kimball the Kollector," Kimball Dinner, 1956-05-22 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- HTH, "You Win By Losing," Commencement Address, Duke University, Durham, North Carolina, 1956-06-04 (Box 3, Folder 32)
- HTH, NYU Commencement, 1956-06-06 (Box 3, Folder 33)
- HTH Remarks, "Can We Meet the Challenge of Universal Education?" Western Michigan College, Kalamazoo, Michigan, 1956-06-09 (Box 3, Folder 34)
- HTH Remarks, "Who Is Responsible for Education?" Commencement -- University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA, 1956-06-13 (Box 3, Folder 35)
- HTH Remarks, "Can We Meet the Challenge of Universal Education?" Commencement - New Jersey State Teachers College, Newark, New Jersey, 1956-06-14 (Box 3, Folder 36)
- HTH Talk at Harvard, "Satisfactions of a College Presidency -- If Any", 1956-06-20 (Box 3, Folder 37)